Finding Aid for President (University of Michigan) records, 1967-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Development
  The Development series documents efforts to attract, report, and acknowledge gifts to the university. The largest portion of the series consists of gift letters expressing appreciation to donors who contributed to the university. These letters extend from the Duderstadt era through the Coleman era. Additionally, there are letters inviting prospective donors to events, letters from donors interested in giving gifts, funding proposals, and financial reports on gifts. There are also materials compiled for President Coleman's use during the Michigan Difference seminars in Florida, where she traveled to West Palm Beach and Naples to give presentations on future plans at the university and meet with donors. They include Coleman's itinerary, talking points, and information on area donors and potential donors.
  - Gift Letters, circa 1994-2009
    - A-CO, 13 folders (Box 508)
    - CR-GEN, 19 folders (Box 509)
    - GEO-KM, 18 folders (Box 510)
    - KN-M, 18 folders (Box 511)
    - N-SI, 20 folders (Box 512)
    - SK-Z, 18 folders (Box 513)
  - Michigan Difference Seminars in Florida, 2007, 2 folders (Box 505)
  - Prospects, 1998-2004, 9 folders (Box 505)
  - Reports, 1991-1999, 3 folders (Box 505)
- Facilities
  The Facilities series contains records on the university's physical resources. The bulk of the series consists of files relating to the dedication, naming, and groundbreaking of various campus buildings and facilities and containing dedication programs, correspondence, invitations, and press releases. Other files contain reports and architectural plans for facility expansions and upgrades.
  - Cabintaxi Ann Arbor/Detroit Projects Overview, 2007 (Box 526)
  - Campus Plan, 2001-2004, 4 folders (Box 522)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2104 ]
  - Dedications, Naming, Groundbreaking (Box 506)
    - General, 1969-2001, 6 folders (Box 506)
    - A. Alfred Taubman Medical Library, 1980 (Box 506)
    - Allan F. and Alene Smith Law Library, 1981-1986 (Box 506)
    - Alumni Center, 1982 (Box 506)
    - Burn Center, 1985-1986 (Box 506)
    - Business Administration, 1982-1984 (Box 506)
    - C.S. Mott Children's Hospital, 1969 (Box 506)
    - Canham Natatorium, 1988 (Box 506)
    - Chemistry Building, 1973-1989 (Box 506)
    - Clarence C. Little Building, 1968 (Box 506)
    - Crisler Arena, 1968 (Box 506)
    - Cyclotron/Positron Emission Lab, 1981-1982 (Box 506)
    - Dennison Building, 1976-1979 (Box 506)
    - Dentistry Building, 1971 (Box 506)
    - Earl V. Moore Building, 1970-1975 (Box 506)
    - Economics (New Quarters in Lorch Hall), 1986 (Box 506)
    - Edward H. Kraus Building, 1973-1986 (Box 506)
    - Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Building, 1984-1986 (Box 506)
    - Elmer D. Mitchell Field, 1980-1981 (Box 506)
    - Engineering Solid-State Electronics Lab, 1987 (Box 506)
    - Fleming Administration Building, 1980-1981 (Box 506)
    - Flint Classroom/Laboratory Building, 1986 (Box 506)
    - Gerald R. Ford Library, 1979 (Box 506)
    - Goebel, Paul, Jr., 1988 (Box 506)
    - Harry G. Kipke Street, 1985 (Box 506)
    - Herbert H. Dow Building, 1975-1989 (Box 506)
    - Industrial Technology Institute, 1985 (Box 506)
    - Institute of Continuing Legal Education Building, 1987 (Box 506)
    - Kellogg Eye Center, 1983-1985 (Box 507)
    - Margaret Dow Towsley Center, 1985 (Box 507)
    - Medical Sciences Research Building, 1983 (Box 507)
    - Medical Sports Facility, 1986 (Box 507)
    - Power Center for the Performing Arts, 1971, 1981 (Box 507)
    - Raoul Wallenberg Plaza, 1987 (Box 507)
    - Ronald McDonald House, 1984-1985 (Box 507)
    - Tappan Hall, 1983-1985 (Box 507)
    - University Hospital and A. Alfred Taubman Health Care Center, 1986 (Box 507)
    - Walter E. Lay Automotive Laboratory, 1956, 1974-1976 (Box 507)
    - William A. Paton Center for Accounting Education and Research, 1976 (Box 507)
  - Hill Auditorium-Restore America National Preservation Honor Award Nomination, 2004, 2 folders (Box 507)
    (includes slides)
  - Law School Expansion Final Report, 2000 (Box 526)
  - Mosher Jordan Renovations and New Dining Center, 2005 (Box 526)
  - South State Street Property Framework Development Plan, 1992 (Box 507)
  - UM-Dearborn Campus Master Plan, 2004 (Box 526)
  - Appeals, 1997 (Box 507)
  - Policies and Guidelines, 1976-1989, 2 folders (Box 507)
  - Requests, 1989-2004, 4 folders (Box 522)
  - Requests, 1989-2004, 5 folders (Box 523)
- Freedom of Information Act (FOIA)
  The Freedom of Information Act series contains letters requesting information under the Freedom of Information Act, responses from FOIA officers granting or denying the requests and appeals, reports analyzing FOIA requests over a calendar year, and correspondence and reports discussing university policy and guidelines with respect to FOIA issues. The files containing requests include attorney-client privileged documents and are closed under the client/patient records restriction.
  - Appeals,1997 (Box 507)
  - Policy Guidelines,1976-1989, 2 folders (Box 507)
  - Requests,1989-2004, 4 folders (Box 522)
  - Requests,1989-2004, 5 folders (Box 522)
- Audio and Visual Materials
  The Audio and Visual Materials series, 1967-2006 (4.5 linear feet and 2.26 GB), consists of photographs, films, audiocassette tapes, online files, videocassette tapes, DVDs, paintings, and drawings relating to the official and ceremonial functions of the president, the president's house, meetings with visiting dignitaries, and student activities. Within the series are subseries for the presidential administrations of Fleming, Shapiro, Duderstadt, Neal, Bollinger, and Coleman.
  - Robben Fleming Administration
    - Photographs
      - Fleming Portraits and Informal Photos (Box 259)
      - Ford (Gerald) Visits to UM (Box 259)
      - Outside University Activities (Box 259)
      - President's House (Box 259)
      - Student Demonstrations 1969 (Box 259)
      - University Activities and Functions
        - General (Box 259)
        - Flint Campus Commencement 1974 (Folder UBImul/B3)
        - Lovell, James and Duke Slater (Folder UBImul/B3)
          (astronauts)
        - McDivitt, James (Folder UBImul/B3)
          (astronaut)
    - Films
      (at outsize location)
      - The President's Inauguration Day [1967] (Reel 1)
        (black and white; approx. 30 minutes; 16 mm; sound in part)
        Summary: Extensive scenes of interiors of the president's house and of the Fleming family on the morning of Fleming's inauguration; shots of reception lines and of ceremonies at Hill Auditorium; reenactment (in sound) of a portion of inaugural address.
      - "1968 President Fleming's First Year" (Reel 2)
        (color; approx. 30 minutes; 16mm; sound).
        Produced by University of Michigan Television Center. Summary: Conversation with Fleming, interspersed with brief interviews with Robert Angell, Hazel Losh, Fritz Crisler, and Arthur M. Ross; also brief clips of student sit-in, UM football, and general campus and classroom scenes.
    - Prints and Paintings
      - President's House (Folder UBImul/B3)
        (painting)
      - School of Music 1978 (Folder UBImul/B3)
        (drawing)
  - Harold Shapiro Administration
    - Photographs
      - Album of Vice President Sussman's Visit to Chosun University October 1984 (Box 259)
      - Portraits of Shapiro (Box 259)
      - Tanner Lecture Series Board 1986 (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - University Activities (Box 259)
        (8x10 color print, Shapiro with ex-presidents Gerald Ford and Jimmy Carter, undated, with negative; six 8x10 black and white prints, Commencement activities, undated)
      - Photograph Albums documenting Shapiro's Presidency, 2 volumes (Box 261)
  - James J. Duderstadt Administration
    - Audiocassettes
      - Remarks to President's club, 5/11/84, 9/21/89, and 11/06/1989, 3 audiocassettes (Box 259)
    - Photographs
      - Athletics
        - Stadium Construction, 2 photographs color 8x10 (Box 259)
        - Tom Harmon with Duderstadt, 1 photographs black and white 8x10 (Box 259)
      - Commencement 1991 (George Bush), 9 folders color (Box 259)
      - Community Education Programs at Museum of Art 1989-1990 (Box 259)
      - Duderstadt in Detroit Outside Various Businesses circa 1990 (Box 259)
      - Duderstadt Portrait (Box 259)
      - Ford Library (Box 259)
        (conferring of President's Medal on Margaret Towsley, November 16, 1990)
      - Information and Library Studies, School of (Box 259)
        (Duderstadt at dedication of Ehrlicher Room, October 4, 1990)
      - Inglis Family and House (Box 259)
        (copy prints)
      - Inglis House Interior 1991 (Box 259)
      - Michigan Ethnic Heritage Studies Center, Ethnic Briefing October 5, 1990 (Box 259)
      - Organization for Tropical Studies 1990
        - President's House (Box 259)
        - Interior circa 1990 (Box 259)
        - Exterior circa 1990 (Box 259)
        - Renovation 1991 (Box 259)
      - Thurnau Professors November 1988 (Box 259)
      - An Afternoon with the Presidents 1992 (Box 259)
        (outsize volume, see Box 260)
      - Duderstadt and wife Anne with Gerald and Betty Ford (Box 259)
      - Duderstadt family 1994 (Box 283)
        (color prints)
      - Lecture by Eijner Jensen 1994 (Box 283)
      - Visit of the Dalai Lama 1994, 1 boxes color; contains contact sheets (Box 283)
      - Jonas Salk Reception April 11, 1995, 2 folders (Box 335)
      - University of Michigan Flags, color proofs (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - Commencement 1993 (Hillary Clinton) (Box 465)
      - Fleming Building Group Photo circa 1987 (Box 465)
      - From the Engineering Case Statement, no date (Box 465)
    - Audiocassette tapes
      - Leadership Retreats
        - January 8, 1991, 2 audiocassettes (Box 259)
          (approx. 120 minutes each)
        - September 4, 1990, 2 audiocassettes (Box 259)
      - Michigan Student Assembly February 1991 students' takeover of Regents' meeting, 1 audiocassettes (Box 259)
        (approx. 90 minutes)
    - Videocassettes
      - Duderstadt Speaking at Rose Bowl 1989 (Box 259)
      - "The Elaine Harden Years" [1991] (Box 259)
        (approx. 30 minutes; color)
        Summary: Made for the retirement of Elaine Harden, Assistant to the Deans of the College of Engineering, 1945-1991 consists of anecdotes and statements by past and present deans of College of Engineering.
      - The Dalai Lama at the University of Michigan 1994 (Box 283)
        (BMC $960)
    - Photographs
      - Photograph Album, "An Afternoon with the Presidents," 1992 (Box 260)
  - 1998-1999
    - Photographs
      - Academic Affairs (Box 325)
      - Athletics (Box 325)
      - Commencement (Box 325)
      - Development (Box 325)
      - ROTC (Box 325)
  - Mary Sue Coleman Administration
    - Best of Michigan A Cappella (Various groups), 2006, .ZIP file
    - Ford Foundation: Mont's Tribute, 2002, .ZIP and .MP4 files
    - DVD's
      - UC 375 -- The University of Michigan Past, Present, and Future (Draft 2.0 of a course by Duderstadt) April 2005 (includes a note from Duderstadt) (Box 465)
    - Videocassettes
      - "Affirmative Action on Trial," August 26, 2003 (Box 465)
      - Ann Arbor Historical Street Exhibit Program, City of Ann Arbor, Michigan undated (Box 465)
  - Homer A. Neal Administration
    - Photographs
      - Faculty Women's Club Reception December 11, 1996 (Box 335)
      - Honorary Degree Dinner December 1996 (Box 335)
  - Lee C. Bollinger Administration
    - Photographs
      - Bollinger Meets With Faculty and Donors at Humanities Camp (Box 335)
      - Bollinger with Colonel Tony G. Daniels of ROTC (Box 335)
      - Commencement with President George Bush, 20 x 24, 4 photographs (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - Engineering Building (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - Nobel Prize 1999 (Box 335)
      - Ceremony (Box 335)
      - Martinus J. G. Veltman, 2 folders (Box 335)
      - Photograph of Bollinger, Gerald Ford and Henry Kissinger at the Naming of the Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy (matted) 2000 (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - U.S. Road Show with Daewoo Representatives 1998 (Box 335)
      - U-M Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers 1999 Conference Attendees, 1999 (Box 335)
      - President and Mrs. Bollinger with Students at President's House September 16, 2001 (Box 465)
    - Other
      - Autographed Poster for the Naming Ceremony of the A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning 1999 (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - Bollinger Farewell Reception December 10, 2001 (audio cassette) (Box 335)
      - Bollinger on Michigan Radio Discussing Life Sciences Initiative April 14, 1999 (audio cassette) (Box 335)
      - Caricature of Athletic Director Tom Goss, Bollinger, and Michigan Stadium [1998] (Box 335)
      - Letter from Arthur Miller (matted) 2000 (Folder UBImul/B3)
      - Letter from Arthur Miller and Photograph 1997 (Box 335)
      - Nobel Prize 1999
        - Invitation to Ceremony and Replica Medallion (Box 335)
        - Posters (Folder UBImul/B3)
        - Posterboard Containing Flag and Emblem Carried on 2nd Skylab Mission (Folder UBImul/B3)
        - Proclamation "Naming of the School of Public Policy The Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy, November 18, 1999" (matted) (Box 335)
        - "Resolution Honoring Lee C. Bollinger on His Departure from the University of Michigan," from Michigan House of Representatives 2001 (Folder UBImul/B3)
        - "Resolution Honoring Lee C. Bollinger on His Inauguration as the Twelfth President of the University of Michigan," from the City of Ann Arbor 1997 (Folder UBImul/B3)
    - Audiocassettes
      - Bollinger's Address to the Detroit Economic Club September 27, 1999 (Box 465)
      - Michigan Radio, Royal Shakespeare at the University of Michigan, Series by Donovan Reynolds 2001 (Box 465)
    - Videocassettes
      - "A Tribute to Arthur Miller," M-Span Special November 12, 2000 (Length: 27:52) (Box 465)
  - Audio Cassettes
    Audio cassette content includes events and issues related to the functions of the president's office as well as radio show recordings such as President Duderstadt, Bo Schembechler, Don Canham, and Phyllis Ocker featured as guests on WJR's radio talk show "Focus." Included in the video tape content is footage from the Arthur Miller International Symposium "Arthur Miller's America: Theater and Culture in a Century of Change," held in 2000, the Royal Shakespeare Company residency at the university in 2001, a university delegation visit to China in 1993, and conversations with President Duderstadt on topics such as research, graduate education, the university's fiscal outlook, and athletics.
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences Induction Ceremony, 10/31/1998 (Box 524)
    - Campus Plan Committee, 3/09/1998, 2 audiocassettes (Box 524)
    - Campus Plan Committee, 3/11/1998 (Box 524)
    - "Focus," WJR
      - J.P. McCarthy, 9/07/1988 (Box 524)
      - James Duderstadt, 9/08/1988 (Box 524)
      - Phyllis Ocker/Don Canham and Bo Schembechler, 5/18/1988, 8/11/1988 (Box 524)
      - Ray Tanter and Lawrence Johnson, 2/02/1988 (Box 524)
    - Inauguration Ceremony-Duderstadt, 10/06/1988, 2 audiocassettes (Box 524)
    - J. Bernard Machen/WJR/Bylaw 14.06, 4/25/1994 (Box 524)
    - Keeping in Touch with U, 5/30/1993 (Box 524)
    - "Kevin Joyce Show," WJR-Regent Deane Baker, 4/27/1994 (Box 524)
    - Manhattan Revisited, A. W. Wamsley, undated (Box 524)
    - A Michigan Radio Sampler: An Audio Program Guide, 7/1990 (Box 524)
    - Michiganensian Board Meeting, 10/14/1991 (Box 524)
    - New President Press Conference, 6/10/1988 (Box 524)
    - Regents Special Meeting/President Selection Committee Report, 6/10/1988, 2 audiocassettes (Box 524)
    - Senate Hearing on Higher Education, 3/13/1992, 2 audiocassettes (Box 524)
    - "State Edition," Michigan Public Radio, 5/23/1994 (Box 524)
    - State of the University-Duderstadt, 10/03/1988 (Box 524)
    - Stone's America Segment on the University of Michigan (BBC), 7/1990 (Box 524)
    - UM Press Conference Research Audit, 9/11/1991, 2 audiocassettes (Box 524)
  - U-matic
    - Conversation with President Duderstadt
      - Graduate Education, 1993 (Box 524)
      - Intercollegiate Athletics, 1993 (Box 524)
      - Research Issues, 1993 (Box 524)
      - The University's Fiscal Outlook, 1993 (Box 524)
  - VHS
    - Admissions Lawsuits News Report, CNN, 1999 (Box 524)
    - Arthur Miller's America: Theater and Culture in a Century of Change, 2000
      - Arthur Miller's Theater: An International Panel, 2 tapes (Box 524)
      - Contemporary Re-Visions: Adaptations of Arthur Miller, 2 tapes (Box 524)
      - "Death of a Salesman" and Beyond, 2 tapes (Box 524)
      - Miller and Autobiography (Box 524)
      - Staging Arthur Miller, 2 tapes (Box 524)
      - "A View from the Bridge" and American Opera 2000 (Box 524)
    - Bollinger National Association for College Admission Counseling (NACAC) Award Acceptance Speech, 2001 (Box 525)
    - China Trip
      - Lieberthal Clips, 1993 (Box 525)
      - Rogel Clips, 1993 (Box 525)
    - Conversation with the President
      - Graduate Education, 1993 (Box 525)
      - Intercollegiate Athletics, 1993 (Box 525)
      - Research Issues, 1993 (Box 525)
    - "The Future of University of Michigan-Flint" Duderstadt Presentation, 1994 (Box 525)
    - Global Citizenship Program, 1992 (Box 525)
    - Michigan at Risk-Higher Education, circa 1994 (Box 525)
    - Royal Shakespeare Company Residency at the University of Michigan, 2001
      - The Art of Acting and Directing Shakespeare, 2 tapes (Box 525)
      - Backstage Tech Stories, Discussion and Coaching with Students, the Musicians and the Composer (Box 525)
      - Behind the Scenes: Stage Managers, Design, and Lighting (Box 525)
      - Community Acting Workshop (Box 525)
      - A Conversation with Adrian Noble (Box 525)
      - A Conversation with Michael Boyd (Box 525)
      - "Now Here a Period of Tumultuous Broils" Lectures
        - Death in the Garden of Iden (2 Henry VI) (Box 525)
        - God Say Amen (Richard III) (Box 525)
        - I am Myself Alone (3 Henry VI) (Box 525)
        - There Comes the Ruin, Here Begins Confusion (1 Henry VI) (Box 525)
      - Shakespeare on Legitimacy and Rebellion, 2 tapes (Box 525)
      - Shakespeare on the Stage (Box 525)
      - Tetralogy Audience before the Show (Box 525)
    - Salk Polio Vaccine Announcement, 1955 (Box 525)
    - UM Community Outreach Office in Lansing Grand Opening Celebration, Channel 6 News, Lansing, 1993 (Box 525)
- Ephemera
  The Ephemera series consists of one subseries: Printing Plates, ca. 1968. The printing plates are color separation plates used to print images of the university schools and colleges flags. The plates are divided up into sets according to school or college flag, and each plate would be used with a specified ink color. Most of the sets include a full color print of their corresponding flag. Color prints of several flags can also be seen on the cover of the January 1968 cover of the Michigan Alumnus.
  - Printing Plates circa 1968
    - President's Flag (Box 466)
    - School of Music (Box 466)
    - College of Engineering (Box 466)
    - Graduate School (Rackham) (Box 466)
    - School of Public Health (2 sets) (Box 466)
    - School of Dentistry (Box 467)
    - School of Social Work (Box 467)
    - School of Nursing (Box 467)
    - School of Natural Resources (Box 467)
    - College of Architecture and Design (Box 467)
    - School of Business Administration (Box 467)
    - Six unidentified sets of printing plates (Box 468)
- Archived University of Michigan President WEBSITE
  The President's Archived Website series documents the mission, activities, policies, and individuals involved in the operation of the Office of the President. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as reports and administrative documents), and information about committees, initiatives, and events. This archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/. Prior to 2010 several snapshots of the President's website were captured locally and stored on CD. They can now be downloaded as ZIP files from Deep Blue, the university's institutional repository.
  - Archived University of Michigan President home page 2001
  - Archived University of Michigan President home page 2005
  - Archived University of Michigan President home page 2008
  - Archived University of Michigan President home page 2009
  - Archived University of Michigan President home page, 2010-[ongoing]
  - University of Michigan President
    - 1996-2014
      (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.
    - 2002, .ZIP file
    - 2005, .ZIP file
    - 2008, .ZIP file
    - 2009, .ZIP file
    - 2010-2014